Guide to the Astle Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Astle correspondence
1757-1803
OSB MSS 30
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
The papers include correspondence mainly regarding Astle's work in the Record Office. There is also correspondence with James Adams about his work on grammar, with Charles Blagden about the Pompeiian excavations, and with Harriot Collinson about her husband's work (John Collinson's "The History and Antiquities of the County of Somerset"). Much of the correspondence is annotated in an unidentified hand.
Astle, Thomas, 1735-1803
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to Thomas Astle.
Language and languages -- Grammars; Pompeii (Extinct city); Antiquarians; Paleographers; Adams, James, 1737-1802; Astle, Thomas, 1735-1803; Blagden, Charles, Sir, 1748-1820; Collinson, Harriot; Collinson, John, 1756 or 1757-1793; Great Britain. Public Record Office
- Correspondence, 1795 Mar 7-1798 Apr 12
  - Adams, James, 1737-1802. 3 ALS to Thomas Astle, Piccadilly, 1795 Mar 7-1798 Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Asks Astle to comment on his book. Includes copy of a song.
  - Ailesbury, Thomas Bruce Brudenell- Bruce, 4th Earl of, 1729-1814. AL (3d person) to Thomas Astle, Hungerford, 1803 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Friendly note.
  - Astle, Thomas, 1735-1803. Memorandum, holograph, on an examination of Parliament Rolls, [n.p.], n.y. Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Reply to inquiry from Lord Chancellor.
  - Aylesford, Heneage Finch, 4th Earl of, 1751-1812. ALS to Thomas Astle, Parkington, 1800 Jul 18
  - Barthelemy, J. ALS to Thomas Astle, Hyde Park, 1787 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Information on the condemnation of Joan of Arc. With Astle's reply.
  - Blagden, Sir Charles, 1748-1820. Letter, extract, to [Thomas Astle], Naples, 1793 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    On Pompeiian expeditions. Copied by Astle.
  - Botetourt, Norborne Berkeley, 4th Baron, 1736-1770. ALS to Thomas Astle, [n.p.], 1764 Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brequigny, Louis George Oudard Fendrix de, 1714-1794. ALS (in French) to Thomas Astle, London, 1763 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    On his work in the Records Office.
  - Butt, John Martin, d. 1741. ALS to Thomas Astle, Oxford, 1762 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chamberlaine, F. ALS to Thomas Astle, Brompton, 1800 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    On the Holbein portraits.
  - Collinson, Harriot (Mrs. John Collinson). ALS to Thomas Astle, Bath, 1795 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Asks Astle's help in defending her late husband's reputation as a historian.
  - Cowper, Henry, 1758-1840. 2 ALS to Thomas Astle, [n.p.], 1789 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Relays instructions from the Lord Chancellor.
  - Eliot, John. ALS to Thomas Astle, [n.p.], n.y. Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Describes what happened on the day he did not wear his own hat.
  - Ferrers, Washington Shirley, 5th Earl, 1722-1778, Staunton Harold. ALS to Thomas Astle, 1778 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Desires information about land titles.
  - Fraser, William. ALS to Thomas Astle, Cleveland Row, 1771 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Asks Astle to deposit papers in trunk. Footnote by Astle reads, "Mr Pitts Correspondence during the War, very private."
  - Hargrave, Francis, 1741?-1821. ALS to Thomas Astle, Boswell Court, 1786 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Inquires whether there once was a keeper of the records with the name Hennage.
  - Howard, John Griffin, 4th Baron of, 1719-1797. ALS (3d person) to Thomas Astle, Burlington St., 1784 Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Official business.
  - Lemon, Robert, 1729-1813. 4 ALS to Thomas Astle, Tower, 1776 May 30-1801 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Friendly and business correspondence.
  - Liverpool, Charles Jenkinson, 1st Earl of, 1727-1808. AL (3d person) to Thomas Astle, Addiscombe Place, 1788 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    About Parliamentary records.
  - Mackenzie, W. ALS to Thomas Astle, Burlington St., 1764 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mayo, Joseph Deane Bourke, 3d Earl of, Abp. of Tuam, 1763-1794. AL (3d person) to Thomas Astle, New Burlington St., 1786 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mellish, Charles. ALS to Thomas Astle, Grosvenor Place, 1775 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Melville, Robert, 1723-1809. AL (fragment ) to the Earl of Buchan, North Frederick Street Court, 1788 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    On antiquarian matters. Endorsed by Thomas Astle.
  - Morin, P. ALS to Thomas Astle, St. James, 1765 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Inquires about an agreement made between the English and French Commissaries, in April or May 1714.
  - Northumberland, Hugh Percy, 4th Duke of, 1742-1817. AL (3d person) to Thomas Astle, North House, 1788 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Sends thanks for his valuable present.
  - Nugent, Robert Craggs Nugent, Earl, 1702-1788. ALS to Thomas Astle, [n.p.], 1775 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ranelagh, Charles Wilkinson Jones, 4th Viscount, 1712-1797. ALS to Thomas Astle, Dublin, 1764 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Requests a copy of the grant to the Earl of Ranelagh, his ancestor.
  - Reeves, John. ALS to Thomas Astle, [n.p.], 1798 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Requests information about silver coinage for Lord Liverpool.
  - Rose, George, 1744-1816. 2 ALS to Thomas Astle, Great George St., 1789 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    On business for the Record Office.
  - Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, 4th Earl of, 1701-1771. 3 ALS to Thomas Astle, Dorchester, 1757 Jun 30-1770 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Asks assistance in verifying his ancestry and excuses Astle from meeting of the "corps."
  - Sharpe, Gregory, 1713-1771. ALS to Thomas Astle, St. Giles, 1768 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Requests information on new importation duties.
  - Stafford, Smyth. AL (3d person) to Thomas Astle, Downing St., 1781 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Thanks for assistance.
  - Valltravers, Rodolph, b.1723. ALS to Thomas Astle, Hamburg, 1790 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Requests Astle vote for him in the appointment of an Assistant Librarian to the British Museum.
  - Vernon, George Venables-Vernon, 2d Baron, 1735-1813. ALS to Thomas Astle, Sadbury, 1801 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Refers to an enclosed letter from his brother, the Bishop of Carlisle, but this letter is wanting.
  - Wallis, John, 1714-1793. ALS to Thomas Astle, Simonburn, 1767 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Reports progress of his book.
  - Walsby, John. ALS to Thomas Astle, [n.p.], 1796 Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Advises cure for rheumatism.
  - Walsh, Mr. AL to Thomas Astle, [n.p.], 1781 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Concerns some coins found at Colony Chapel, three miles from St. Albans.
  - Walsingham, Thomas de Grey, 2d Baron, 1748-1818. ALS to Thomas Astle, Upper Harley St., 1781 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    On records of the Board of Trade.
  - Wappeler, William. ALS to Thomas Astle, Ghent, 1776 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Watts, John. ALS to Thomas Astle, Beverly, 1797 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 39)